Best of enemies. Deadliest of friends.
Pat Garrett & Billy the Kid is a western, drama film directed by Sam Peckinpah.
Pat Garrett is hired as a lawman on behalf of a group of wealthy New Mexico
cattle barons to bring down his old friend Billy the Kid.
Pat Garrett, played by James Coburn.
Billy the Kid, played by Kris Kristofferson.
Sheriff Kip McKinney, played by Richard Jaeckel.
Mrs. Baker, played by Katy Jurado.
Lemuel, played by Chill Wills.
Chisum, played by Barry Sullivan.
Pat Garrett and Billy the Kid is a 1973 American revisionist Western film directed by Sam Peckinpah, written by Rudy Wurlitzer, and starring James
Coburn, Kris Kristofferson, Richard Jaeckel, Katy Jurado, Chill Wills, Barry Sullivan, Jason Robards, Slim Pickens and Bob Dylan.
The film is about an aging Pat Garrett (Coburn), hired as a lawman by a group of wealthy New
Mexico cattle barons to bring down his old friend Billy the Kid (Kristofferson).
Dylan composed the score and songs for the film, most prominently "Knockin' on Heaven's Door", which were released on its
soundtrack album the same year and nominated for a Grammy Award for Album of Best Original Score (Dylan).
The movie was filmed on location in Durango, Mexico, and was nominated for two BAFTA
Awards for Film Music (Dylan) and Most Promising Newcomer (Kristofferson).
The film was noted for behind-the-scenes battles between
Peckinpah and the studio, Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer.
Soon after completion, the film was taken away from the director and substantially re-edited, resulting in
a truncated version released to theaters and largely disowned by cast and crew members.
Peckinpah's preview version was released on video in 1988, leading to a re-evaluation, with
many critics hailing it as a mistreated classic and one of the era's best films.
It is ranked 126th on Empire magazine's list of The
500 Greatest Movies of All Time.
The film explores themes of sheriff, gore, aging, lawlessness, breast.
The tone is emotional.